              <GPOTABLE CDEF="s50,5" COLS="2" OPTS="L2">
                <TTITLE>Miscellaneous</TTITLE>
                <BOXHD>
                  <CHED H="1"> </CHED>
                  <CHED H="1">Rating</CHED>
                </BOXHD>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="01">5324 Diaphragm, rupture of, with herniation. Rate under diagnostic code 7346</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="01">5325 Muscle injury, facial muscles. Evaluate functional impairment as seventh (facial) cranial nerve neuropathy (diagnostic code 8207), disfiguring scar (diagnostic code 7800), etc. Minimum, if interfering to any extent with mastication—10</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="01">5326 Muscle hernia, extensive. Without other injury to the muscle—10</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="01">5327 Muscle, neoplasm of, malignant (excluding soft tissue sarcoma)—100
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="21">
                    <E T="04">Note:</E> A rating of 100 percent shall continue beyond the cessation of any surgery, radiation treatment, antineoplastic chemotherapy or other therapeutic procedures. Six months after discontinuance of such treatment, the appropriate disability rating shall be determined by mandatory VA examination. Any change in evaluation based upon that or any subsequent examination shall be subject to the provisions of § 3.105(e) of this chapter. If there has been no local recurrence or metastasis, rate on residual impairment of function.
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="01">5328 Muscle, neoplasm of, benign, postoperative. Rate on impairment of function, <E T="03">i.e.</E>, limitation of motion, or scars, diagnostic code 7805, etc</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="01">5329 Sarcoma, soft tissue (of muscle, fat, or fibrous connective tissue)—100
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="21">
                    <E T="04">Note:</E> A rating of 100 percent shall continue beyond the cessation of any surgery, radiation treatment, antineoplastic chemotherapy or other therapeutic procedures. Six months after discontinuance of such treatment, the appropriate disability rating shall be determined by mandatory VA examination. Any change in evaluation based upon that or any subsequent examination shall be subject to the provisions of § 3.105(e) of this chapter. If there has been no local recurrence or metastasis, rate on residual impairment of function.</ENT>
                </ROW>
