              <GPOTABLE CDEF="s50,6" COLS="2" OPTS="L2">
                <BOXHD>
                  <CHED H="1"> </CHED>
                  <CHED H="1">Rating</CHED>
                </BOXHD>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="11">7700 Anemia, hypochromic-microcytic and megaloblastic, such as iron-deficiency and pernicious anemia:</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Hemoglobin 5gm/100ml or less, with findings such as high output congestive heart failure or dyspnea at rest</ENT>
                  <ENT>100</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Hemoglobin 7gm/100ml or less, with findings such as dyspnea on mild exertion, cardiomegaly, tachycardia (100 to 120 beats per minute) or syncope (three episodes in the last six months)</ENT>
                  <ENT>70</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Hemoglobin 8gm/100ml or less, with findings such as weakness, easy fatigability, headaches, lightheadedness, or shortness of breath</ENT>
                  <ENT>30</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Hemoglobin 10gm/100ml or less with findings such as weakness, easy fatigability or headaches</ENT>
                  <ENT>10</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Hemoglobin 10gm/100ml or less, asymptomatic</ENT>
                  <ENT>0
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW EXPSTB="01">
                  <ENT I="11">
                    <E T="04">Note:</E> Evaluate complications of pernicious anemia, such as dementia or peripheral neuropathy, separately.
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW EXPSTB="00">
                  <ENT I="11">7702 Agranulocytosis, acute:</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Requiring bone marrow transplant, or; requiring transfusion of platelets or red cells at least once every six weeks, or; infections recurring at least once every six weeks</ENT>
                  <ENT>100</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <PRTPAGE P="456"/>
                  <ENT I="03">Requiring transfusion of platelets or red cells at least once every three months, or; infections recurring at least once every three months</ENT>
                  <ENT>60</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Requiring transfusion of platelets or red cells at least once per year but less than once every three months, or; infections recurring at least once per year but less than once every three months</ENT>
                  <ENT>30</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Requiring continuous medication for control</ENT>
                  <ENT>10
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW EXPSTB="01">
                  <ENT I="22">
                    <E T="04">Note:</E> The 100 percent rating for bone marrow transplant shall be assigned as of the date of hospital admission and shall continue with a mandatory VA examination six months following hospital discharge. Any change in evaluation based upon that or any subsequent examination shall be subject to the provisions of § 3.105(e) of this chapter.
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW EXPSTB="00">
                  <ENT I="11">7703 Leukemia:</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">With active disease or during a treatment phase</ENT>
                  <ENT>100</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="13">Otherwise rate as anemia (code 7700) or aplastic anemia (code 7716), whichever would result in the greater benefit.
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW EXPSTB="01">
                  <ENT I="22">
                    <E T="04">Note:</E> The 100 percent rating shall continue beyond the cessation of any surgical, radiation, antineoplastic chemotherapy or other therapeutic procedures. Six months after discontinuance of such treatment, the appropriate disability rating shall be determined by mandatory VA examination. Any change in evaluation based upon that or any subsequent examination shall be subject to the provisions of § 3.105(e) of this chapter. If there has been no recurrence, rate on residuals.
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW EXPSTB="00">
                  <ENT I="11">7704 Polycythemia vera:</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">During periods of treatment with myelosuppressants and for three months following cessation of myelosuppressant therapy</ENT>
                  <ENT>100</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Requiring phlebotomy</ENT>
                  <ENT>40</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Stable, with or without continuous medication</ENT>
                  <ENT>10
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW EXPSTB="01">
                  <ENT I="22">
                    <E T="04">Note:</E> Rate complications such as hypertension, gout, stroke or thrombotic disease separately.
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW EXPSTB="00">
                  <ENT I="11">7705 Thrombocytopenia, primary, idiopathic or immune:</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Platelet count of less than 20,000, with active bleeding, requiring treatment with medication and transfusions</ENT>
                  <ENT>100</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Platelet count between 20,000 and 70,000, not requiring treatment, without bleeding</ENT>
                  <ENT>70</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Stable platelet count between 70,000 and 100,000, without bleeding</ENT>
                  <ENT>30</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Stable platelet count of 100,000 or more, without bleeding</ENT>
                  <ENT>0</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="01">7706 Splenectomy</ENT>
                  <ENT>20
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW EXPSTB="01">
                  <ENT I="22">
                    <E T="04">Note:</E> Rate complications such as systemic infections with encapsulated bacteria separately.
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW EXPSTB="00">
                  <ENT I="11">7707 Spleen, injury of, healed.</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="13">Rate for any residuals.</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="11">7709 Hodgkin's disease:</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">With active disease or during a treatment phase</ENT>
                  <ENT>100
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW EXPSTB="01">
                  <ENT I="22">
                    <E T="04">Note:</E> The 100 percent rating shall continue beyond the cessation of any surgical, radiation, antineoplastic chemotherapy or other therapeutic procedures. Six months after discontinuance of such treatment, the appropriate disability rating shall be determined by mandatory VA examination. Any change in evaluation based upon that or any subsequent examination shall be subject to the provisions of § 3.105(e) of this chapter. If there has been no local recurrence or metastasis, rate on residuals.
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW EXPSTB="00">
                  <ENT I="11">7710 Adenitis, tuberculous, active or inactive.</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="13">Rate under §§ 4.88c or 4.89 of this part, whichever is appropriate.</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="11">7714 Sickle cell anemia:</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">With repeated painful crises, occurring in skin, joints, bones or any major organs caused by hemolysis and sickling of red blood cells, with anemia, thrombosis and infarction, with symptoms precluding even light manual labor</ENT>
                  <ENT>100</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">With painful crises several times a year or with symptoms precluding other than light manual labor</ENT>
                  <ENT>60</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Following repeated hemolytic sickling crises with continuing impairment of health</ENT>
                  <ENT>30</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Asymptomatic, established case in remission, but with identifiable organ impairment</ENT>
                  <ENT>10
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW EXPSTB="01">
                  <ENT I="22">
                    <E T="04">Note:</E> Sickle cell trait alone, without a history of directly attributable pathological findings, is not a ratable disability. Cases of symptomatic sickle cell trait will be forwarded to the Director, Compensation Service, for consideration under § 3.321(b)(1) of this chapter.
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW EXPSTB="00">
                  <ENT I="11">7715 Non-Hodgkin's lymphoma:</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">With active disease or during a treatment phase</ENT>
                  <ENT>100
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW EXPSTB="01">
                  <ENT I="22">
                    <E T="04">Note:</E> The 100 percent rating shall continue beyond the cessation of any surgical, radiation, antineoplastic chemotherapy or other therapeutic procedures. Six months after discontinuance of such treatment, the appropriate disability rating shall be dtermined by mandatory VA examination. Any change in evaluation based upon that or any subsequent examination shall be subject to the provisions of § 3.105(e) of this chapter. If there has been no local recurrence or metastasis, rate on residuals.
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW EXPSTB="00">
                  <ENT I="11">7716 Aplastic anemia:</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Requiring bone marrow transplant, or; requiring transfusion of platelets or red cells at least once every six weeks, or; infections recurring at least once every six weeks</ENT>
                  <ENT>100</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Requiring transfusion of platelets or red cells at least once every three months, or; infections recurring at least once every three months</ENT>
                  <ENT>60</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Requiring transfusion of platelets or red cells at least once per year but less than once every three months, or; infections recurring at least once per year but less than once every three months</ENT>
                  <ENT>30</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Requiring continuous medication for control</ENT>
                  <ENT>10
                  </ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW EXPSTB="01">
                  <ENT I="22">
                    <E T="04">Note:</E> The 100 percent rating for bone marrow transplant shall be assigned as of the date of hospital admission and shall continue with a mandatory VA examination six months following hospital discharge. Any change in evaluation based upon that or any subsequent examination shall be subject to the provisions of § 3.105(e) of this chapter.</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW EXPSTB="00">
                  <ENT I="11">7717 AL amyloidosis (primary amyloidosis)</ENT>
                  <ENT>100</ENT>
                </ROW>
