              <GPOTABLE CDEF="s50,5" COLS="2" OPTS="L2">
                <TTITLE>The Epilepsies</TTITLE>
                <BOXHD>
                  <CHED H="1"> </CHED>
                  <CHED H="1">Rating</CHED>
                </BOXHD>
                <ROW EXPSTB="00">
                  <ENT I="12">A thorough study of all material in §§ 4.121 and 4.122 of the preface and under the ratings for epilepsy is necessary prior to any rating action.</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="22">8910 Epilepsy, grand mal.</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="12">Rate under the general rating formula for major seizures.</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="22">8911 Epilepsy, petit mal.</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="12">Rate under the general rating formula for minor seizures.</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="12">
                    <E T="04">Note</E> (1): A major seizure is characterized by the generalized tonic-clonic convulsion with unconsciousness.</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="12">
                    <E T="04">Note</E> (2): A minor seizure consists of a brief interruption in consciousness or conscious control associated with staring or rhythmic blinking of the eyes or nodding of the head (“pure” petit mal), or sudden jerking movements of the arms, trunk, or head (myoclonic type) or sudden loss of postural control (akinetic type).</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="12">General Rating Formula for Major and Minor Epileptic Seizures:</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Averaging at least 1 major seizure per month over the last year</ENT>
                  <ENT>100</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Averaging at least 1 major seizure in 3 months over the last year; or more than 10 minor seizures weekly</ENT>
                  <ENT>80</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">Averaging at least 1 major seizure in 4 months over the last year; or 9-10 minor seizures per week</ENT>
                  <ENT>60</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">At least 1 major seizure in the last 6 months or 2 in the last year; or averaging at least 5 to 8 minor seizures weekly</ENT>
                  <ENT>40</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">At least 1 major seizure in the last 2 years; or at least 2 minor seizures in the last 6 months</ENT>
                  <ENT>20</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="03">A confirmed diagnosis of epilepsy with a history of seizures</ENT>
                  <ENT>10</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="12">
                    <E T="04">Note</E> (1): When continuous medication is shown necessary for the control of epilepsy, the minimum evaluation will be 10 percent. This rating will not be combined with any other rating for epilepsy.</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="12">
                    <E T="04">Note</E> (2): In the presence of major and minor seizures, rate the predominating type.</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="12">
                    <E T="04">Note</E> (3): There will be no distinction between diurnal and nocturnal major seizures.</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="22">8912 Epilepsy, Jacksonian and focal motor or sensory.</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="22">8913 Epilepsy, diencephalic.</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="12">Rate as minor seizures, except in the presence of major and minor seizures, rate the predominating type.</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="22">8914 Epilepsy, psychomotor.</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="12">Major seizures:</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="13">Psychomotor seizures will be rated as major seizures under the general rating formula when characterized by automatic states and/or generalized convulsions with unconsciousness.</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="12">Minor seizures:</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="13">Psychomotor seizures will be rated as minor seizures under the general rating formula when characterized by brief transient episodes of random motor movements, hallucinations, perceptual illusions, abnormalities of thinking, memory or mood, or autonomic disturbances.</ENT>
                </ROW>

                <TNOTE>Mental Disorders in Epilepsies: A nonpsychotic organic brain syndrome will be rated separately under the appropriate diagnostic code (e.g., 9304 or 9326). In the absence of a diagnosis of non-psychotic organic psychiatric disturbance (psychotic, psychoneurotic or personality disorder) if diagnosed and shown to be secondary to or directly associated with epilepsy will be rated separately. The psychotic or psychroneurotic disorder will be rated under the appropriate diagnostic code. The personality disorder will be rated as a dementia (e.g., diagnostic code 9304 or 9326).<PRTPAGE P="474"/>
                </TNOTE>
                <TNOTE>Epilepsy and Unemployability: (1) Rating specialists must bear in mind that the epileptic, although his or her seizures are controlled, may find employment and rehabilitation difficult of attainment due to employer reluctance to the hiring of the epileptic.</TNOTE>
                <TNOTE>(2) Where a case is encountered with a definite history of unemployment, full and complete development should be undertaken to ascertain whether the epilepsy is the determining factor in his or her inability to obtain employment.</TNOTE>
                <TNOTE>(3) The assent of the claimant should first be obtained for permission to conduct this economic and social survey. The purpose of this survey is to secure all the relevant facts and data necessary to permit of a true judgment as to the reason for his or her unemployment and should include information as to:</TNOTE>
                <TNOTE>(a) Education;</TNOTE>
                <TNOTE>(b) Occupations prior and subsequent to service;</TNOTE>
                <TNOTE>(c) Places of employment and reasons for termination;</TNOTE>
                <TNOTE>(d) Wages received;</TNOTE>
                <TNOTE>(e) Number of seizures.</TNOTE>
                <TNOTE>(4) Upon completion of this survey and current examination, the case should have rating board consideration. Where in the judgment of the rating board the veteran's unemployability is due to epilepsy and jurisdiction is not vested in that body by reason of schedular evaluations, the case should be submitted to the Compensation Service or the Director, Pension and Fiduciary Service.</TNOTE>
