              <GPOTABLE CDEF="s200,8" COLS="2" OPTS="L2">
                <TTITLE>Rating Formula for Eating Disorders</TTITLE>
                <BOXHD>
                  <CHED H="1"> </CHED>
                  <CHED H="1">Rating</CHED>
                </BOXHD>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="01" O="xl">Self-induced weight loss to less than 80 percent of expected minimum weight, with incapacitating episodes of at least six weeks total duration per year, and requiring hospitalization more than twice a year for parenteral nutrition or tube feeding.</ENT>
                  <ENT>100</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="01" O="xl">Self-induced weight loss to less than 85 percent of expected minimum weight with incapacitating episodes of six or more weeks total duration per year.</ENT>
                  <ENT>60</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="01" O="xl">Self-induced weight loss to less than 85 percent of expected minimum weight with incapacitating episodes of more than two but less than six weeks total duration per year.</ENT>
                  <ENT>30</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="01" O="xl">Binge eating followed by self-induced vomiting or other measures to prevent weight gain, or resistance to weight gain even when below expected minimum weight, with diagnosis of an eating disorder and incapacitating episodes of up to two weeks total duration per year.</ENT>
                  <ENT>10</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                  <ENT I="01" O="xl">Binge eating followed by self-induced vomiting or other measures to prevent weight gain, or resistance to weight gain even when below expected minimum weight, with diagnosis of an eating disorder but without incapacitating episodes.</ENT>
                  <ENT>0</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <TNOTE>
                  <E T="02">Note 1:</E> An incapacitating episode is a period during which bed rest and treatment by a physician are required.</TNOTE>
                <TNOTE>
                  <E T="02">Note 2:</E> Ratings under diagnostic codes 9201 to 9440 will be evaluated using the General Rating Formula for Mental Disorders. Ratings under diagnostic codes 9520 and 9521 will be evaluated using the General Rating Formula for Eating Disorders.</TNOTE>
